<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Indigenous Values Initiative</title>
	<atom:link href="https://indigenousvalues.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://indigenousvalues.org</link>
	<description>NYA WEÑHA SKÄ NOÑH: Thank you for being well</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 19:54:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/cropped-indigenousvalues-color-512x512-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Indigenous Values Initiative</title>
	<link>https://indigenousvalues.org</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>2020 Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival &#038; Randy Hall Memorial Tournament</title>
		<link>https://indigenousvalues.org/laxweekend20/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DJ Brett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 02:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lacrosse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#laxweekend18]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haudenosaunee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lacrosse weekened]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[laxweekend]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Onondaga Lake]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wooden stick festival]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://indigenousvalues.org/?p=5263</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Come Play Where Lacrosse Originated Deyhontsigwa’ehs: The Creator’s Game, Lacrosse Weekend 2020 Saturday September 12-Sunday September 13, 2020 Onondaga Lake Park, Liverpool, New York in the heart of Onondaga Nation Territory 5th Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival The festival features wooden &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/laxweekend20/" aria-label="2020 Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival &#038; Randy Hall Memorial Tournament">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 style="text-align: center;">Come Play Where Lacrosse Originated</h3>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">Deyhontsigwa’ehs: The Creator’s Game,<br />
Lacrosse Weekend 2020</h4>
<h5 style="text-align: center;">Saturday September 12-Sunday September 13, 2020<br />
Onondaga Lake Park, Liverpool, New York<br />
in the heart of Onondaga Nation Territory</h5>
<h3>5th Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival</h3>
<p>The festival features wooden lacrosse stick makers and other Haudenosaunee crafters. The festival takes place on the sports fields on the south of Onondaga Lake Park. There will be traditional singing and dancing with traditional Haudenosaunee foods and speakers. This event will be educational and entertaining for the whole family.</p>
<p>There are several exciting events taking place at the same time:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h4>Wooden Stick Festival (9:00am-5:00pm)</h4>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Rand Hall Masters Wooden Stick Lacrosse Tournament (9:00am-4:00pm)</h4>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The Haudenosaunee (Called “Iroquois” by colonists) are the originators and keepers of the game known today as “lacrosse.” Deyhontsigwa’ehs (“They Bump Hips,” in the Onondaga Language) goes back millennia and is also known as “The Creator’s Game” and the “Medicine Game” The Onondaga Nation is the “Central Fire” of the Haudenosaunee Confederacy of six nations (Mohawk, Onondaga, Oneida, Cayuga, Seneca, and Tuscarora). The Haudenosaunee Confederacy was founded on the shore of Onondaga Lake––now called Syracuse, NY. Over 1000 years ago. Deyhontsigwa’ehs played an integral role in establishing “The Great Law of Peace.” Today throughout Haudenosaunee territory the “Medicine Game” is still played in ceremony. We are dedicated to re-establishing a Haudenosaunee presence back at Onondaga Lake where this game was originally played.</p>
<h3>Our Sponsors.</h3>
<p>Contact &#105;nfo&#64;indige&#110;ous&#118;&#97;&#108;&#117;e&#115;.&#111;rg to be a sponsor of this event.</p>
<h3>Our Collaborative Spirit.</h3>
<p>The Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival is a collaboration between the <a href="https://aila.ngo/">American Indian Law Alliance</a> and the <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/">Indigenous Values Initiative</a>. We are proud to collaborate with one another on such an important event. One of the many lessons we can all learn from Deyhontsigwa’ehs (lacrosse) is the importance of collaboration and working together.</p>
<h3>Second Annual Randy Hall Masters<br />
Wooden Stick Lacrosse Tournament</h3>
<p>There will be referees, a tent for changing, a box sized field marked out on the grass with 4&#215;4 nets by Onondaga Lake. Players will be responsible for helmets and gloves, and wooden sticks. Teams will be responsible for their jerseys. Wooden sticks are preferred but not required.</p>
<ul>
<li>Prizes
<ul>
<li><em>First Prize</em>: Leather Game Ball, trophy, <strong>$700</strong> cash</li>
<li><em>Second Prize:</em> Plaque, and <strong>$300</strong> cash.</li>
<li><em>Third Prize:</em> Plaque and <strong>$300</strong> cash.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The tournament registration fee:
<ul>
<li>$300 Early Bird registration per team until 3/31/2020</li>
<li>$400 Regular registration per team until 8/31/2020</li>
<li>$500 Walk-up per team until 9/28/19</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Individual registration for house team(s) (includes jersey and lunch)
<ul>
<li>Early Bird registration $75 per person until 3/31/2020</li>
<li>Regular registration $100 per person until 8/31/2020</li>
<li>Walk-up registration $125 per person until 9/28/2020</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Get Involved</h3>
<div class="row"> <div class="col-md-4  "> <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/thohnendatek-randy-hall-memorial-old-sticks-tournament-registration/" target="_self" class="kad-icon-box-75  kad-icon-box "><i class="icon-trophy" style="font-size:48px;"></i></a><style type="text/css" media="screen">.kad-icon-box-75 {background:#dddddd;} .kad-icon-box-75, .kad-icon-box-75 h1, .kad-icon-box-75 h2, .kad-icon-box-75 h3, .kad-icon-box-75 h4, .kad-icon-box-75 h5 {color:#49147f !important;} .kad-icon-box-75:hover {background:;} .kad-icon-box-75:hover, .kad-icon-box-75:hover h1, .kad-icon-box-75:hover h2, .kad-icon-box-75:hover h3, .kad-icon-box-75:hover h4, .kad-icon-box-75:hover h5 {color:#079999 !important;}</style>
<h5 style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/thohnendatek-randy-hall-memorial-old-sticks-tournament-registration/">Enter the Tournament</a></h5>
</div><div class="col-md-4  "> <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/sponsor-packages/" target="_self" class="kad-icon-box-17  kad-icon-box "><i class="icon-users3" style="font-size:48px;"></i></a><style type="text/css" media="screen">.kad-icon-box-17 {background:#dddddd;} .kad-icon-box-17, .kad-icon-box-17 h1, .kad-icon-box-17 h2, .kad-icon-box-17 h3, .kad-icon-box-17 h4, .kad-icon-box-17 h5 {color:#49147f !important;} .kad-icon-box-17:hover {background:;} .kad-icon-box-17:hover, .kad-icon-box-17:hover h1, .kad-icon-box-17:hover h2, .kad-icon-box-17:hover h3, .kad-icon-box-17:hover h4, .kad-icon-box-17:hover h5 {color:#079999 !important;}</style>
<h5 style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/sponsor-packages/">Be a Partner </a></h5>
</div><div class="col-md-4  "> <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/vendor-application/" target="_self" class="kad-icon-box-98  kad-icon-box "><i class="icon-tags" style="font-size:48px;"></i></a><style type="text/css" media="screen">.kad-icon-box-98 {background:#dddddd;} .kad-icon-box-98, .kad-icon-box-98 h1, .kad-icon-box-98 h2, .kad-icon-box-98 h3, .kad-icon-box-98 h4, .kad-icon-box-98 h5 {color:#49147f !important;} .kad-icon-box-98:hover {background:;} .kad-icon-box-98:hover, .kad-icon-box-98:hover h1, .kad-icon-box-98:hover h2, .kad-icon-box-98:hover h3, .kad-icon-box-98:hover h4, .kad-icon-box-98:hover h5 {color:#079999 !important;}</style>
<h5 style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/vendor-application/">Be A Vendor</a></h5>
</div></div>
<h4>About Randy Hall</h4>
<p>Thomas Randall “Randy” Hall, Akwesasne Mohawk Wolf Clan, passed away January 18, 2018. He served in Vietnam with US Army (1965-68) and participated in the 1972 AIM take-over of the Bureau of Indian Affairs in Washington D.C. He loved sports and was deeply involved with the Onondaga Athletic Club where he played and coached lacrosse and basketball. One of his favorite things to do was to travel and play in tournaments. In his memory, the Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival honors Randy by naming the wooden sticks tournament after him.</p>
<p>The inaugural Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival was held at Onondaga Lake in 2013. Previously the game had been played exclusively on Haudenosaunee Nation territories, but in 2013, Randy Hall asked Philip P. Arnold and Sandy Bigtree for help in bringing the game back to Onondaga Lake––its place of origin. It was here the Peacemaker arrived well over 1,000 years ago to bring peace to five warring nations. Few realize that Deyhontsigwa’ehs, the Creator’s Game, was an integral part of this peacemaking process. This ancient game is still played ceremonially among the Haudenosaunee. It is played hard, but always played to foster good relationships between human beings and the natural world.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>#laxweekend20</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">###</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Christian Domination and the Failure of ‘Truth and Reconciliation’</title>
		<link>https://indigenousvalues.org/christian-domination/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DJ Brett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 17:05:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christianity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[docd]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[docdis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[doctrine of discovery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haudenosaunee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Onondaga Nation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sovereignty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Syracuse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[treaties]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://indigenousvalues.org/?p=2038</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hi all, It is with great regret that we have decided to cancel this year’s Doctrine of Christian Discovery (DoCD) conference “Christian Domination and the Failure of ‘Truth and Reconciliation.’” It has been rescheduled for 22-23 August 2020. Of course &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/christian-domination/" aria-label="Christian Domination and the Failure of ‘Truth and Reconciliation’">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi all,</p>
<p>It is with great regret that we have decided to cancel this year’s Doctrine of Christian Discovery (DoCD) conference “Christian Domination and the Failure of ‘Truth and Reconciliation.’” It has been rescheduled for 22-23 August 2020. Of course we will fully refund everyone who has registered for the conference.</p>
<p>As all of you know, our sponsoring organizations—the Indigenous Values Initiative (IVI) and the American Indian Law Alliance (AILA)—are deeply involved with the work of revealing and dismantling the DoCD and we do not want this cancelation to slow any of the momentum that has been built around this issue over the last few years. However, our small volunteer organizations have been involved in some new and exciting directions that require our undivided attention over the next few months. This week we all decided that missing one year of the DoCD conference was unavoidable and that this postponement would not be too disruptive.</p>
<p>In recognition of the 100 year anniversary of the Women’s right to vote, one of our initiatives for 2020 is to focus on the Haudenosaunee influence on the Women’s Suffrage Movement (following Sally Roesch Wagner’s work and new book on the topic). Our 2020 DoCD conference will likely focus on Women and their roles in traditional matrilineal societies and how that has been systematically disrupted by religion. If you have other ideas on this topic or others we would like to hear them.</p>
<p>We will be refunding you the ticket amount here shortly. Unfortuantely we are unable to refund the eventbrite.com fee.</p>
<p>Instead we would like to offer you the following options to covery the eventbrite processing fee:</p>
<p>A coupon to the Indigenous Values store.<br />
A check for the processing fee amount mailed to you. if you would like us to do that please email &#105;&#110;&#102;o&#64;in&#100;ige&#110;ou&#115;&#118;a&#108;ue&#115;&#46;&#111;rg and give us your mailing address</p>
<p>Thank you for your patience with us and, again, we are sorry to miss seeing you all again this year.</p>
<p>Phil, Betty, Sandy, Gail, Joe and Adam</p>
<hr />
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">A conference in Onondaga Nation Territory, at Syracuse University and Skä·noñh—Great Law of Peace Center</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">Saturday and Sunday, 17-18 August 2019.</p>
<h2><strong>Description:</strong></h2>
<p>This conference continues discussions between religious communities and Indigenous Peoples about the Doctrine of Christian Discovery (DOCD) so that real healing can occur. “Truth and Reconciliation” efforts in settler-colonial states have the appearance of resolving the history of conquest and domination but often do not result in a healing of Indigenous Peoples and their lands. Using words like reconciliation, repudiation, domination, discovery, conquest, missionization, colonialism and settler-colonialism, or referring to Indigenous Peoples in the singular or as populations, issues or groups, has consequences. Noam Chomsky, George Lakoff, and Steven Newcomb remind us that word choice matters and, although these concepts appear benign, they actually perpetuate and give cover to a violent past. The DOCD continues to be a matter of urgent concern for Indigenous Peoples around the world. It has emboldened trans-national corporations to further their extraction practices everywhere forcing standoffs and migration of Indigenous Peoples. Our lineup of speakers will address international migration issues and the connection between the DOCD and the destruction of Mother Earth.</p>
<ul>
<li>The event is co-sponsored by the <a href="https://aila.ngo">American Indian Law Alliance</a> and <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org">Indigenous Values Initiative</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://religionnews.com/2019/07/08/christian-domination-and-the-failure-of-truth-and-reconciliation/">Religion News Service Press Release</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><strong>Confirmed speakers:</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>Oren Lyons (<a href="https://www.onondaganation.org/">Onondaga Nation Council of Chiefs</a>)</li>
<li>Tadodaho Sid Hill (<a href="https://www.onondaganation.org/">Onondaga Nation Council of Chiefs</a>)</li>
<li>Beverly Jacobs (<a href="http://www.uwindsor.ca/indigenous-peoples/302/beverly-jacobs">Law, University of Windsor</a>)</li>
<li>Betty Lyons (<a href="https://aila.ngo">American Indian Law Alliance</a>)</li>
<li>Sandy Bigtree (Indigenous Values Initiative)</li>
<li>Joe Heath (General Council for the <a href="https://www.onondaganation.org/">Onondaga Nation</a>)</li>
<li>Phil Arnold (<a href="http://religion.syr.edu">Religion, Syracuse University</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><strong>Conference fees</strong>:</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://christiandomination.eventbrite.com">Early-bird registration</a> $125 until 30 June 2019</li>
<li><a href="https://christiandomination.eventbrite.com">Regular registration</a> $150 until 31 July 2019</li>
<li><a href="https://christiandomination.eventbrite.com">Late registration</a> $175 until 15 August</li>
<li><a href="https://christiandomination.eventbrite.com">Walkup registration</a> $200</li>
</ul>
<a href="https://christiandomination.eventbrite.com/" id="kadbtn25" target="_blank" class="kad-btn btn-shortcode kad-btn-primary lg-kad-btn " style="background-color:#8224e3; border: 2px solid; border-color:#000000; border-radius:6px; color:#ffffff;" onMouseOver="this.style.color=&#039;#ffffff&#039;" onMouseOut="this.style.color=&#039;#ffffff&#039;">Register Now <i class='icon-arrow-up-right'></i></a>
<h3><strong>Scholarships:</strong></h3>
<p>There are a limited number of scholarships available to cover the registration fee.</p>
<p><em>If you need a scholarship, please send an email to inf&#111;&#64;indigeno&#117;&#115;v&#97;l&#117;&#101;s.o&#114;g and <em>briefly</em> tell us who you are, why you would like to attend and any work you do connected to dismantling the &#8216;doctrine of discovery&#8217; and why you are applying for a scholarship. Please put &#8216;scholarship request&#8217; in the subject of the email.</em></p>
<p><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/give/">			<i class="icon-link4 " style="font-size:14px; display:inline-block; color:#444; 			"></i>
				 If you want to contribute a scholarship for others to attend the conference you can donate to the conference</a>.</p>
<h3>Hotels</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.marriott.com/events/start.mi?id=1555340255180&amp;key=GRP" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.marriott.com/events/start.mi?id%3D1555340255180%26key%3DGRP&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1556224441663000&amp;usg=AFQjCNE14kQ_T3g6uvwhZg37TiCIVsgAVw"><strong>Book your group rate for SU Religion.</strong></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3>Draft Schedule</h3>
<p class="p1">(draft 26 June 19)</p>
<h4 class="p1"><b>Saturday 17 August</b></h4>
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1">8:00 AM — <b>Onondaga Lake Water Ceremony</b> &#8211; at Onondaga Lake
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1">Meet at pier near Salt Museum</li>
<li class="li1"><strong>Opening address</strong> by Tadodaho Sidney Hill</li>
<li class="li1"><b>Water Ceremony</b> conducted by Betty Lyons and Eve Reyes-Aguirre
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1">(Bring waters from your home territories for this event)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="li1">9:00 AM — <b>Haudenosaunee breakfast</b> — at the Skanonh Center
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1"><b>Orientation</b> to the Skä·noñh—Great Law of Peace Center, Sandy Bigtree and Phil Arnold</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="li1">11:09 AM — <b>Registration</b> — at Falk College, SU</li>
<li class="li1">Noon-1:30 PM — <b>Lunch</b> — followed by the film “<i>The Doctrine of Discovery</i>” (1 hour) and a talk with Steven Newcomb.</li>
<li class="li1">1:30-3:30 PM — <strong> International work panel</strong> — Grant Auditorium, SU
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1">Panelists: Betty Lyons, Tupac Enrique Acosta, Eve Reyes-Aguirre, &amp; Jake Edwards</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="li1">4:00-6:00 PM — <b>Law Panel</b> — Grant Auditorium, SU
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1"><b>Panelists</b>: Joe Heath, Steve Newcomb, Dana Lloyd</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="li1">7:00-9:00 PM — dinner — Falk College, SU</li>
</ul>
<h4 class="p1">Sunday 18 August</h4>
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1">8:00 AM—light breakfast (Falk, SU catering)</li>
<li class="li1">9:00-11:00 AM—Religion panel  — Grant Auditorium, SU
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1"><b>Panelists</b>: Philip P. Arnold, Adam DJ Brett, Eglute Trinkauskaite, Sandra Bigtree</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="li1">11:30 AM-1:00 PM—<b>Listening circle on what people are doing about the DoD </b>— Falk College, SU
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1">Facilitated by Gail Bundy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="li1">1:00-2:30 PM—<b>lunch</b> —Falk College, SU
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1">During lunch the Onondaga youth will perform social songs</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="li1">2:30-4:00 PM—<strong>Oren Lyons Keynote, “Truth and Reconciliation”</strong> — Grant Auditorium, SU
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1">Followed by a discussion</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="li1">4:30-5:30 PM—<strong>Final thoughts and concerns, “Value Change for Survival” </strong>— Grant Auditorium, SU</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exploring the Haudenosaunee understanding of the environment</title>
		<link>https://indigenousvalues.org/exploring-haudenosaunee-understanding-environment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DJ Brett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 18:47:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haudenosaunee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://indigenousvalues.org/?p=1993</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Indigenous Values Initiative will be hosting a one day training seminar for educators on the theme of exploring the Haudenosaunee understanding of the environment. The event is open to all educators who work in K-12 settings, public parks, private &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/exploring-haudenosaunee-understanding-environment/" aria-label="Exploring the Haudenosaunee understanding of the environment">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Indigenous Values Initiative will be hosting a one day training seminar for educators on the theme of exploring the Haudenosaunee understanding of the environment. The event is open to all educators who work in K-12 settings, public parks, private parks, and more. If you work and serve in an educational capacity this event is for you. There will be a traditional Haudenosaunee lunch provided to all the seminar participants. This seminar will build on the recently developed K-12 curriculum: <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/exploring-haudenosaunee-and-scientific-perspectives/">Exploring Haudenosaunee and scientific perspectives with guides for Middle and High School</a>.</p>
<h3>Event Details:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Date</strong>: Saturday 3 August from 10:00am to 3:00pm.</li>
<li><strong>Location</strong>: <a href="https://www.skanonhcenter.org/">Skä•noñh</a> &#8211; Great Law of Peace Center, A Haudenosaunee Heritage Center.</li>
<li><strong>Map</strong>: <a href="https://goo.gl/maps/PQKWdmGbBo1CfbrA8">6680 Onondaga Lake Parkway, Liverpool, New York 13088</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Lunch</strong>: A traditional Haudenosaunee lunch will be provided.</li>
<li><strong>Space is limited so register ASAP</strong>.</li>
<li>This event is <strong>free</strong> and open to educators.</li>
<li>There is a stipend of $50.00 for selected participants</li>
</ul>
<h4>Speakers:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Catherine Landis, Ph.D. (SUNY-ESF), environmental history of the area</li>
<li>Tom Mackey, Ph.D Student (SUNY-SF), focuses on museums and education</li>
<li>Betty Lyons, American Indian Law Alliance</li>
<li>Sandra Bigtree, Indigenous Values Initiative</li>
<li>Philip P. Arnold, Indigenous Values Initiative</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Curriculum</strong>:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/exploring-haudenosaunee-and-scientific-perspectives/">Exploring Haudenosaunee and scientific perspectives with guides for Middle and High School</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Register Below</h4>
[contact-form-7]
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WCNY presents Rumble</title>
		<link>https://indigenousvalues.org/wcny-presents-rumble/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DJ Brett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 15:26:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[indigenous]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[native americans]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sovereignty]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://indigenousvalues.org/?p=1945</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rumble Indie Lens Screening Thank you all for your partnership to bring the Indie Lens Screening of “Rumble: The Indians Who Rocked the World” to our community. Following are the details and agenda for the event. In red are action &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/wcny-presents-rumble/" aria-label="WCNY presents Rumble">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Rumble Indie Lens Screening</strong></p>
<p>Thank you all for your partnership to bring the Indie Lens Screening of “Rumble: The Indians Who Rocked the World” to our community. Following are the details and agenda for the event. In red are action items. If there is anyone else involved who should be included, please forward this information along. And if you have any edits/suggestions, please let me know.</p>
<p>WCNY’s Marketing team will update our website posting to reflect our additional partners/details (Indigenous Values Initiative), as well as update social media posts and news release/calendar alerts. We will encourage advance registration, since seating at the Auburn Public Theater is limited (please confirm total number of possible seats at 180). Please continue to promote this event through your networks and share the registration link: <a href="http://www.wcny.org/events/rumble-the-indians-that-rocked-the-world/" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=http://www.wcny.org/events/rumble-the-indians-that-rocked-the-world/&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1547780694790000&amp;usg=AFQjCNHA634mWyXtmaQ-B__RWSsFI_l6rw">http://www.wcny.org/events/rumble-the-indians-that-rocked-the-world/</a></p>
<h3><strong>DESCRIPTION: </strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>RUMBLE</em></strong> brings to light a profound and missing chapter in the history of American music: the Indigenous influence. Featuring music icons Charley Patton, Mildred Bailey, Link Wray, Jimi Hendrix, Jesse Ed Davis, Buffy Sainte-Marie, Robbie Robertson, Randy Castillo, and Taboo, <strong><em>RUMBLE</em></strong> shows how these pioneering Native musicians helped shape the soundtracks of our lives.</li>
<li>A discussion guide with details about the film and bios of the featured artists has been shared with Rob and Sandy.</li>
<li>Broadcast Premiere on PBS will be Monday, Jan. 21, 2019.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>SCREENING JANUARY 16, 2019:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At 6:30 P.M., Courtney will share information about the Equal Rights Heritage Center, then instruct attendees to make their way to the Auburn Public Theater for screening.</li>
<li>(Partnership with Philip Arnold, founding director <a href="http://www.skanonhcenter.org/" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=http://www.skanonhcenter.org/&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1547780694790000&amp;usg=AFQjCNHh0b2FcS7uIoDSANitoN2t_7PCQQ">Skä·noñh, Great Law of Peace Center</a>, and president of <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://indigenousvalues.org/&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1547780694790000&amp;usg=AFQjCNGXtRD8dVJPxav_x-jwFxBsjQffjw">Indigenous Values Initiative</a> and Sandy Bigtree, musician and member of Indigenous Values Initiative)7-9 p.m. screening at Auburn Public Theater, Auburn, NY. (contact is Angela Daddabbo)</li>
<li>Registration table to be provided. WCNY will man registration table.</li>
<li>Podium and microphone to be provided by Center, as well as some seating.</li>
<li>Octane Social House (Rob Otterstatter) will be coordinating the reception and providing hors d’oeuvres and beverages.5-7 p.m. reception at Equal Rights Heritage Center, Auburn (contact is Courtney Rae Kasper)</li>
<li>At 6:50 p.m., Cristina will introduce Indie Lens Screening of film Rumble.At 8:30 p.m., Sandy Bigtree and Phil Arnold will moderate community conversation around film.Movie will play from 7 p.m. to 8:30. Approximate Running Time: 86 minutes. DVDs were provided to Rob, who will get them to Angela to test in advance.</li>
<li>At 9:00 p.m., Angela will thank guests for coming.</li>
</ul>
<p>Cristina will bring surveys to Auburn Public Theater for placement on all seats.</p>
<p>At 5:40 p.m., Mayor Quill will introduce Sandy Bigtree and Phil Arnold (bios: <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/about/our-team/" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://indigenousvalues.org/about/our-team/&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1547780694790000&amp;usg=AFQjCNHLfiWJIAFGu6UD26qNRdo6VEKbyw">https://indigenousvalues.org/about/our-team/</a>) to discuss Indigenous Values Initiative and introduce conversation topics/question for audience feedback and participation.</p>
<ul>
<li>At 5:30 p.m., Rob will make introductory remarks and introduce Mayor Quill.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.wcny.org/wcny-presents-free-preview-of-rumble-the-indians-who-rocked-the-world/"><span style="color: #ffffff;">			<i class="icon-link4 kad-circle-iconclass" style="font-size:16px; display:inline-block; color:#444; background:#385c73;			"></i>
				</span> Learn more at WCNY</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2019 Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival &#038; Randy Hall Memorial Tournament</title>
		<link>https://indigenousvalues.org/laxweekend19/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DJ Brett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 19:23:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Lacrosse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haudenosaunee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[indigenous peoples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[laxweekend]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[laxweekend19]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sovereignty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wooden sticks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://indigenousvalues.org/?p=1927</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Saturday September 28-Sunday September 29, 2019. Onondaga Lake Park, Liverpool, New York in the heart of Onondaga Nation Territory]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 style="text-align: center;">Come Play where Lacrosse Originated</h3>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">Deyhontsigwa&#8217;ehs: The Creator&#8217;s Game, <br />Lacrosse Weekend 2019</h4>
<h5>Saturday September 28-Sunday September 29, 2019<br />Onondaga Lake Park, Liverpool, New York<br />in the heart of Onondaga Nation Territory</h5>
<h3>4th Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival</h3>
<p>The festival features wooden lacrosse stick makers and other Haudenosaunee crafters. The festival takes place on the sports fields on the south of Onondaga Lake Park. There will be traditional singing and dancing with traditional Haudenosaunee foods and speakers. This event will be educational and entertaining for the whole family.</p>
<p>There are three exciting events taking place at the same time:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h4>Wooden Stick Festival (9:00am-5:00pm)</h4>
</li>
</ul>
<h4><em>Social Dancing Noon Saturday and Sunday</em></h4>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Wooden lacrosse stick artisans,
<ul>
<li>Alf Jacques will have a booth showcasing his collection and how to make wooden sticks. He will be doing presentations throughout the day.</li>
<li>Travis Gabriel and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/tionatakwentelacrosse/">Tionatakwente Lacrosse</a> will be selling lacrosse sticks at the event.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>traditional Haudenosaunee crafters</li>
<li>Haudenosaunee dancing</li>
<li>Haudenosaunee speakers</li>
<li>Free and fun for the whole family</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Rand Hall Masters Wood Stick Lacrosse Tournament (9:00am-4:00pm)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Free to watch</li>
<li>registration fee to play (to cover refs and rentals)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<h4><a href="http://spirittwinslacrosse.com">Spirit Twins Box Lacrosse Clinic</a> (Noon on Saturday)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Noon on Saturday</li>
<li>Box clinic for 9-13 year olds. </li>
<li><a href="http://spirittwinslacrosse.com">spirittwinslacrosse.com</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The Haudenosaunee (Called &#8220;Iroquois&#8221; by colonists) are the originators and keepers of the game known today as &#8220;lacrosse.&#8221; Deyhontsigwa&#8217;ehs (&#8220;They Bump Hips,&#8221; in the Onondaga Language) goes back millennia and is also known as &#8220;The Creator&#8217;s Game&#8221; and the &#8220;Medicine Game&#8221; The Onondaga Nation is the &#8220;Central Fire&#8221; of the Haudenosaunee Confederacy of six nations (Mohawk, Onondaga, Oneida, Cayuga, Seneca, and Tuscarora). The Haudenosaunee Confederacy was founded on the shore of Onondaga Lake––now called Syracuse, NY. Over 1000 years ago. Deyhontsigwa&#8217;ehs played an integral role in establishing &#8220;The Great Law of Peace.&#8221; Today throughout Haudenosaunee territory the &#8220;Medicine Game&#8221; is still played in ceremony. We are dedicated to re-establishing a Haudenosaunee presence back at Onondaga Lake where this game was originally played.</p>
<h3>Our Collaborative Spirit.</h3>
<p>The Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival is a collaboration between the <a href="https://aila.ngo">American Indian Law Alliance</a> and the <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/">Indigenous Values Initiative</a>. We are proud to collaborate with one another on such an important event. One of the many lessons we can all learn from Deyhontsigwa&#8217;ehs (lacrosse) is the importance of collaboration and working together.</p>
<h3>Our Sponsors</h3>
<p>Special thanks to our Sponsors:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h4><a href="http://cuse.com">Syracuse University Athletics</a></h4>
</li>
<li>
<h4><a href="https://tewaaraton.com">The Tewaaraton Foundation</a></h4>
</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3>Second Annual Randy Hall Masters <br />Wooden Stick Lacrosse Tournament</h3>
<p>There will be referees, a tent for changing, a box sized field marked out on the grass with 4&#215;4 nets by Onondaga Lake. Players will be responsible for helmets and gloves, and wooden sticks. Teams will be responsible for their jerseys. Wooden sticks are preferred but not required.</p>
<ul>
<li>Prizes
<ul>
<li><em>First Prize</em>: Leather Game Ball, trophy, <strong>$700</strong> cash</li>
<li><em>Second Prize:</em> Plaque, and <strong>$300</strong> cash.</li>
<li><em>Third Prize:</em> Plaque and <strong>$300</strong> cash.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The tournament registration fee:
<ul>
<li>$300 Early Bird registration per team until 3/31/2019</li>
<li>$400 Regular registration per team until 8/31/19 </li>
<li>$500 Walk-up per team until 9/28/19</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Individual registration for house team(s) (includes jersey and lunch)
<ul>
<li>Early Bird registration $75 per person until 3/31/2019</li>
<li>Regular registration $100 per person until 8/31/2019</li>
<li>Walk-up registration $125 per person until 9/28/2019</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/randy-hall-tournament-rules.pdf" id="kadbtn36" target="_blank" class="kad-btn btn-shortcode kad-btn-primary  " style="background-color:#49137f; border: 2px solid; border-color:#000000; border-radius:6px; color:#ffffff;" onMouseOver="this.style.color=&#039;#ffffff&#039;" onMouseOut="this.style.color=&#039;#ffffff&#039;">Tournament Rules <i class='icon-download'></i></a>
<h3>Get Involved</h3>
<div class="row"> <div class="col-md-4  "> <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/thohnendatek-randy-hall-memorial-old-sticks-tournament-registration/" target="_self" class="kad-icon-box-47  kad-icon-box "><i class="icon-trophy" style="font-size:48px;"></i></a><style type="text/css" media="screen">.kad-icon-box-47 {background:#dddddd;} .kad-icon-box-47, .kad-icon-box-47 h1, .kad-icon-box-47 h2, .kad-icon-box-47 h3, .kad-icon-box-47 h4, .kad-icon-box-47 h5 {color:#49147f !important;} .kad-icon-box-47:hover {background:;} .kad-icon-box-47:hover, .kad-icon-box-47:hover h1, .kad-icon-box-47:hover h2, .kad-icon-box-47:hover h3, .kad-icon-box-47:hover h4, .kad-icon-box-47:hover h5 {color:#079999 !important;}</style>
<h5 style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/thohnendatek-randy-hall-memorial-old-sticks-tournament-registration/">Enter the Tournament</a></h5>
</div><div class="col-md-4  "> <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/sponsor-packages/" target="_self" class="kad-icon-box-77  kad-icon-box "><i class="icon-users3" style="font-size:48px;"></i></a><style type="text/css" media="screen">.kad-icon-box-77 {background:#dddddd;} .kad-icon-box-77, .kad-icon-box-77 h1, .kad-icon-box-77 h2, .kad-icon-box-77 h3, .kad-icon-box-77 h4, .kad-icon-box-77 h5 {color:#49147f !important;} .kad-icon-box-77:hover {background:;} .kad-icon-box-77:hover, .kad-icon-box-77:hover h1, .kad-icon-box-77:hover h2, .kad-icon-box-77:hover h3, .kad-icon-box-77:hover h4, .kad-icon-box-77:hover h5 {color:#079999 !important;}</style>
<h5 style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/sponsor-packages/">Be a Partner </a></h5>
</div><div class="col-md-4  "> <a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/vendor-application/" target="_self" class="kad-icon-box-72  kad-icon-box "><i class="icon-tags" style="font-size:48px;"></i></a><style type="text/css" media="screen">.kad-icon-box-72 {background:#dddddd;} .kad-icon-box-72, .kad-icon-box-72 h1, .kad-icon-box-72 h2, .kad-icon-box-72 h3, .kad-icon-box-72 h4, .kad-icon-box-72 h5 {color:#49147f !important;} .kad-icon-box-72:hover {background:;} .kad-icon-box-72:hover, .kad-icon-box-72:hover h1, .kad-icon-box-72:hover h2, .kad-icon-box-72:hover h3, .kad-icon-box-72:hover h4, .kad-icon-box-72:hover h5 {color:#079999 !important;}</style>
<h5 style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/vendor-application/">Be A Vendor</a></h5>
</div></div>
<h4>About Randy Hall</h4>
<p>Thomas Randall “Randy” Hall, Akwesasne Mohawk Wolf Clan, passed away January 18, 2018. He served in Vietnam with US Army (1965-68) and participated in the 1972 AIM take-over of the Bureau of Indian Affairs in Washington D.C. He loved sports and was deeply involved with the Onondaga Athletic Club where he played and coached lacrosse and basketball. One of his favorite things to do was to travel and play in tournaments. In his memory, the Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival honors Randy by naming the wooden sticks tournament after him.</p>
<p>The inaugural Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival was held at Onondaga Lake in 2013. Previously the game had been played exclusively on Haudenosaunee Nation territories, but in 2013, Randy Hall asked Philip P. Arnold and Sandy Bigtree for help in bringing the game back to Onondaga Lake––its place of origin. It was here the Peacemaker arrived well over 1,000 years ago to bring peace to five warring nations. Few realize that Deyhontsigwa’ehs, the Creator’s Game, was an integral part of this peacemaking process. This ancient game is still played ceremonially among the Haudenosaunee. It is played hard, but always played to foster good relationships between human beings and the natural world.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3>Hotels</h3>
<p><a href="https://hamptoninn.hilton.com/en/hp/groups/personalized/S/SYRCYHX-WSF-20190928/index.jhtml?WT.mc_id=POG">Registration link</a> Hotel Information</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Group Name:</td>
<td>Wooden Stick Festival-Indigenous</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Group Code:</td>
<td>WSF</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Check-in:</td>
<td>28-SEP-2019</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Check-out:</td>
<td>29-SEP-2019</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hotel Name:</td>
<td><a href="https://hamptoninn.hilton.com/en/hp/hotels/index.jhtml?ctyhocn=SYRCYHX" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://hamptoninn.hilton.com/en/hp/hotels/index.jhtml?ctyhocn%3DSYRCYHX&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1556224441850000&amp;usg=AFQjCNFrciFWcnIBGNA47WQpwiC3JRqWUw">Hampton Inn Syracuse Clay</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hotel Address:</td>
<td>3948 State Route 31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> </td>
<td>Liverpool, New York</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> </td>
<td>13090</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Phone Number:</td>
<td>315-443-3861</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>#laxweekend19</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Maine-Wabanaki REACH &#8211; Post-Event Summary for &#8220;Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery: What are our next steps?&#8221;</title>
		<link>https://indigenousvalues.org/maine-wabanaki-reach-post-event-summary-for-taking-on-the-doctrine-of-discovery-what-are-our-next-steps/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DJ Brett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Dec 2018 04:13:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[doctrine of discovery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[event]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haudenosaunee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://indigenousvalues.org/?p=1915</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thank you to Maine-Wabanaki REACH Board Member Diane Oltarzewski for this exaging post event write up for &#8220;Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery: What are our next steps?&#8221; Here is a brief highlight from the article: And then the panel discussions began! &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/maine-wabanaki-reach-post-event-summary-for-taking-on-the-doctrine-of-discovery-what-are-our-next-steps/" aria-label="Maine-Wabanaki REACH &#8211; Post-Event Summary for &#8220;Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery: What are our next steps?&#8221;">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you to <a href="http://www.mainewabanakireach.org/_taking_on_the_doctrine_of_discovery_what_are_our_next_steps">Maine-Wabanaki REACH</a> Board Member Diane Oltarzewski for this exaging post event write up for &#8220;<a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/taking-on-the-doctrine-of-discovery-what-are-our-next-steps/">Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery: What are our next steps</a>?&#8221; Here is a brief highlight from the article:</p>
<blockquote><p>And then the panel discussions began! Everyone present was there to grapple with what action is needed to effect real change. I heard many wise voices new to me: Freida Jean Jacques (Onondaga) Turtle Clan Mother, speaking against racism and about the Good Mind. Steven Newcomb (Shawnee/Lenape), who has analyzed the cognitive and Biblical underpinnings of conquest and domination carried out in North America to subjugate originally free and independent Indigenous Nations. His book Pagans in the Promised Land: Decoding the Doctrine of Christian Discovery is eye-opening and a must-read. Tupac Enrique Acosta (Aztec), who asked &#8220;When did light divide into white and less-than-white?&#8221; Joe Heath (Onondaga) Legal Counsel, who documented examples of how the Doctrine of Christian Discovery has become encoded in U.S. law over the centuries, differentiating between Native &#8220;occupancy&#8221; (a lesser claim) and the &#8220;absolute title&#8221; conferred by so-called discovery. Jake Edwards (Onondaga) who said: &#8220;Colonizers are in deep trouble because they don&#8217;t recognize their broken heart&#8230;we have to put our minds together if we want change to happen.&#8221;</p>
<p>A water ceremony was held on the shore of the terminally polluted Lake Onondaga &#8211; I&#8217;d brought a little jar of water from the Passagassawakeag River to mingle with other waters from many sources, joining in a healing prayer.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.mainewabanakireach.org/_taking_on_the_doctrine_of_discovery_what_are_our_next_steps">For more see Oltarzewski&#8217;s article: &#8220;Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery: What are our next steps?&#8221;</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Diversity and Inclusion in Lacrosse</title>
		<link>https://indigenousvalues.org/diversity-and-inclusion-in-lacrosse/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DJ Brett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Nov 2018 19:12:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Lacrosse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#laxweekend18]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haudenosaunee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Onondaga Lake]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Onondaga Nation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Syracuse]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://indigenousvalues.org/?p=1871</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The November edition of US Lacrosse Magazine has two important stories about diversity and inclusion in Lacrosse (Deyhontsigwa’ehs). The first article discusses changes being made in Dakota Premier Lacrosse League and the creation of a Native American Advisory Council for US &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/diversity-and-inclusion-in-lacrosse/" aria-label="Diversity and Inclusion in Lacrosse">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The November edition of <a href="https://www.qgdigitalpublishing.com/publication/?i=533369&amp;ver=html5">US Lacrosse Magazine</a> has two important stories about diversity and inclusion in Lacrosse (Deyhontsigwa’ehs). The first article discusses changes being made in Dakota Premier Lacrosse League and the creation of a <a href="https://www.qgdigitalpublishing.com/publication/?i=533369&amp;ver=html5&amp;p=18">Native American Advisory Council for US Lacrosse</a>. The second article is a study in making traditional wooden sticks with <a href="https://www.qgdigitalpublishing.com/publication/?i=533369&amp;ver=html5&amp;p=18">Alf Jacques of the Onondaga Nation</a>. There are continuing challenges in the lacrosse community to embrace the values of the Haudenosaunee embodied in the “Creator’s Game.”  We applaud The “Tewaaraton Foundation’s” efforts to increase the level of respect and knowledge about the indigenous roots of the game.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li>US Lacrosse Adopts Native American Advisory Council. [<a href="https://www.qgdigitalpublishing.com/publication/?i=533369&amp;ver=html5&amp;p=16">magazine</a>] [<a href="https://www.uslaxmagazine.com/fuel/us-lacrosse/us-lacrosse-adopts-native-american-advisory-council">online</a>]</li>
<li>Making Wooden Sticks. [<a href="https://www.qgdigitalpublishing.com/publication/?i=533369&amp;ver=html5&amp;p=18">magazine</a>]</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>3rd Woodenstick Festival a Success</title>
		<link>https://indigenousvalues.org/3rd-woodenstick-festival-a-success/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DJ Brett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 21:18:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lacrosse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#laxweekend18]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haudenosaunee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Onondaga Lake]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Onondaga Nation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Syracuse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wooden stick]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://indigenousvalues.org/?p=1849</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[“HAUDENOSAUNEE WOODEN STICK LACROSSE FESTIVAL” AND “RANDY HALL MEMORIAL MASTER’S TOURNAMENT” Thank you to all the wonderful people who attended the Deyhontsigwa’ehs Lacrosse Weekend, which was comprised of the Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Lacrosse Festival and Randy Hall Memorial Masters Tournament &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/3rd-woodenstick-festival-a-success/" aria-label="3rd Woodenstick Festival a Success">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>“HAUDENOSAUNEE WOODEN STICK LACROSSE FESTIVAL” AND “RANDY HALL MEMORIAL MASTER’S TOURNAMENT”</h3>
<p>Thank you to all the wonderful people who attended the Deyhontsigwa’ehs Lacrosse Weekend, which was comprised of the Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Lacrosse Festival and Randy Hall Memorial Masters Tournament at Onondaga Lake Park. Attendees to the festival were treated to traditional Native American Arts &amp; Crafts , traditional wooden lacrosse sticks, and some exhilarating master’s level lacrosse along with plenty of time and space for people to shoot around and play lacrosse together.</p>
<p><div style="width: 720px;" class="wp-video"><!--[if lt IE 9]><script>document.createElement('video');</script><![endif]-->
<video class="wp-video-shortcode" id="video-1849-1" width="720" height="406" preload="metadata" controls="controls"><source type="video/mp4" src="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/slomo-video-alf-jacques-lacrosse-sticks-collections.mp4?_=1" /><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/slomo-video-alf-jacques-lacrosse-sticks-collections.mp4">https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/slomo-video-alf-jacques-lacrosse-sticks-collections.mp4</a></video></div></p>
<p>Festival attendees were excited to visit with world-renowned wooden stick makers like Alf Jacques (Onondaga Nation), and Tionatakwente Travis Gabriel (Mohawk Nation) were on hand. Alf Jacques showed off his collection of Lacrosse sticks from all over Turtle Island, especially from the Indigenous Peoples of North and Central Americas. He demonstrated the wide varieties of sticks and styles of play for the game of Lacrosse as well as showing off some of his own handiwork. Three festival goers were excited to pick up their sticks from Alf Jacques after having waited several years. Tionatakwente Travis Gabriel, another highly sought after stick maker, brought some of his sticks to sell and promises next year to bring wooden and leather balls, as well as many attendees, were asking him about these items.</p>
<h4>Thanksgiving Address</h4>
<p><a class="hoverZoomLink" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="1855" data-permalink="https://indigenousvalues.org/3rd-woodenstick-festival-a-success/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake/" data-orig-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,1848" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.2&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone 6 Plus&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1538301829&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;4.15&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;32&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.00050505050505051&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="laxweekend18-onondaga-lake" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-300x170.jpg" data-large-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-1024x580.jpg" class="alignleft size-large wp-image-1855 hoverZoomLink" src="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-1024x580.jpg" alt="Onondaga Lake" width="1024" height="580" data-id="1855" srcset="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-1024x580.jpg 1024w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-300x170.jpg 300w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-768x435.jpg 768w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-600x340.jpg 600w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-1696x960.jpg 1696w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-848x480.jpg 848w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-520x294.jpg 520w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/laxweekend18-onondaga-lake-260x147.jpg 260w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a>Tadodaho Sid Hill of the Haudenosaunee Confederacy opened #laxweekend18 with the Thanksgiving Address or the Words that Come Before All Else. The Address thanked the Creator, the earth, and all the animals for their many gifts and outlined humanities responsibilities to care for the animals and the earth. Tadodaho Sid Hill spoke of the importance of Onondaga Lake as a sacred site of the Onondagans and for the Haudenosaunee Confederacy and pointed out the tragedy of the lake’s polluted status. The polluted nature of the lake heightens the importance of the Creator’s Game (Lacrosse) being played with wooden sticks and a leather ball here at the lake.</p>
<h4>Master’s Tournament</h4>
<p><a class="hoverZoomLink" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="1853" data-permalink="https://indigenousvalues.org/3rd-woodenstick-festival-a-success/onondaga-old-sticks-mohawk-team/" data-orig-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team-300x300.jpg" data-large-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team-1024x1024.jpg" class="alignleft size-medium wp-image-1853 hoverZoomLink" src="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team-300x300.jpg" alt="Onondaga Old Sticks and Mohawk Rez dogs" width="300" height="300" data-id="1853" srcset="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team-300x300.jpg 300w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team-150x150.jpg 150w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team-768x768.jpg 768w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team-600x600.jpg 600w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team-100x100.jpg 100w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Onondaga-Old-Sticks-Mohawk-team.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>The Masters Wooden Stick Tournament served as a reminder that the world is sick and in need of healing. Players, referees, and attendees shared their excitement that the Creator’s Game (Lacrosse) was being played traditionally at such a prominent location. The wooden stick tournament while not a medicine game reminded all those who attended the earth and humanity’s need for medicine and healing. Three teams participated in the inaugural Randy Hall Memorial Tournament, the Onondaga Old Sticks, The Kanehsatà:ke Rez Dogs, and the Buffalo/ Cattaraugus Old Sticks. The games were played with a good mind and close intense competition. It was exciting to see players using multiple different types of wooden sticks from a wide variety of eras. In a fitting tribute to Randy Hall the Onondaga Old Sticks placed Randy’s old jersey on a chair throughout the games and spoke about how they could tell that Randy’s Spirit was with them throughout the games. Wooden stick maker Travis Gabriel, lead the Rez Dogz to second place, and Buffalo/Cattaraugus team played very well and came in third place.  Beautiful First-place trophy and Second and Third place plaques were designed by Tuscarora Woodworks.  The game leather ball was also awarded to the Onondaga Masters team.</p>
<h4>Speakers</h4>
<p><div id="attachment_1852" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a class="hoverZoomLink" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1852" data-attachment-id="1852" data-permalink="https://indigenousvalues.org/3rd-woodenstick-festival-a-success/johnson-jimerson-speaking/" data-orig-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking-300x300.jpg" data-large-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking-1024x1024.jpg" class="wp-image-1852 size-medium hoverZoomLink" src="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking-300x300.jpg" alt="Johnson Jimerson" width="300" height="300" data-id="1852" srcset="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking-300x300.jpg 300w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking-150x150.jpg 150w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking-768x768.jpg 768w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking-600x600.jpg 600w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking-100x100.jpg 100w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Johnson-Jimerson-Speaking.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1852" class="wp-caption-text">Johnson Jimerson</p></div></p>
<p>Johnson Jimerson (Cattaraugus/Seneca Nation), a defenseman for the 2018 Iroquois Nationals team, spoke about his unique journey to making the team and going to Israel for the FIL World Lacrosse Championship and being on the Bronze medal team. Jimerson spoke about what it means for him to be a traditional Haudenosaunee Confederacy man and how the Great Law of Peace has been a guiding force in his life. He remarked that one of the hardest parts of playing international lacrosse is being pressured to play with a plastic stick. A stick which is not traditional and is dead and lacking in spirit. Jimerson noted that the thing about a wooden stick is that it is alive and has a spirit. You are connected to the stick, and the stick is connected to you. You play better with a wooden stick.</p>
<p><div id="attachment_1856" style="width: 269px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a class="hoverZoomLink" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Oren-Lyons.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1856" data-attachment-id="1856" data-permalink="https://indigenousvalues.org/3rd-woodenstick-festival-a-success/oren-lyons/" data-orig-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Oren-Lyons.jpg" data-orig-size="1357,1571" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.2&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone 6 Plus&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1538312366&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;4.15&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;32&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.0055555555555556&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Oren-Lyons" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Oren-Lyons-259x300.jpg" data-large-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Oren-Lyons-885x1024.jpg" class="wp-image-1856 size-medium hoverZoomLink" src="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Oren-Lyons-259x300.jpg" alt="Oren Lyons" width="259" height="300" data-id="1856" srcset="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Oren-Lyons-259x300.jpg 259w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Oren-Lyons-768x889.jpg 768w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Oren-Lyons-885x1024.jpg 885w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Oren-Lyons-600x695.jpg 600w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Oren-Lyons.jpg 1357w" sizes="(max-width: 259px) 100vw, 259px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1856" class="wp-caption-text">Oren Lyons</p></div></p>
<p>As Faithkeeper Oren Lyons spoke an eagle circled over the lake and the lacrosse field where the Championship game was taking place. Lyons delivered a stirring call to the audience to understand the origins of lacrosse, why it is much more than a game, and how it can bring healing to one’s life. Lyons noted that by playing with wooden sticks and a leather ball the players were honoring the Creator, while also being respectful of Haudenosaunee Confederacy tradition. To paraphrase Lyons, when you play lacrosse with a Wooden Stick you play with all the trees and animals in the world. That’s why you carry it with you. Plastic sticks are dead sticks and don’t have spirit. Lyons went on to connect the how the skills necessary to excel at lacrosse are intimately connected to traditional indigenous ways of knowing in general and Haudenosaunee ways in particular. One example, Lyons utilized was seven-generation thinking. He pointed out that one common aspect of indigenous peoples today is thinking seven generations into the past and seven generations into the future. A generation is not just ten years as some people might think but more like seventy to eighty years, the average span of a person’s life. Lyons called on the audience to think with a long view about the ancestors and the future and he asked: “where are the US and Canadian leaders who thinking seven generations?” Lyons concluded his talk by asking the audience to embrace thinking with the good mind and to understand just how interconnected all life truly is.</p>
<h4>Social Dancing</h4>
<p>Dancers from the Onondaga Nation, led by Sherri Waterman-Hopper, appeared at the Wooden Stick Festival on both Saturday and Sunday.  Their social dancing was one of the highlights of the Festival.</p>
<h4>Thank you</h4>
<p>Thank you to our sponsors (Syracuse University, Nike, Gannon&#8217;s Ice Cream, and Summit Credit Union) and the many excellent crafters and vendors, especially Potato Skins Express for serving up a delicious variety of potato skins throughout the events. Finally thank you to the broader lacrosse community for talking about the Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival on their sites, blogs, podcasts, and social media.</p>
<h4>Next Year</h4>
<p><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/IVI-team.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="1857" data-permalink="https://indigenousvalues.org/3rd-woodenstick-festival-a-success/ivi-team/" data-orig-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/IVI-team.jpg" data-orig-size="960,720" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="IVI-team" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/IVI-team-300x225.jpg" data-large-file="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/IVI-team.jpg" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1857" src="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/IVI-team.jpg" alt="Indigenous Values Initiative" width="960" height="720" data-id="1857" srcset="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/IVI-team.jpg 960w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/IVI-team-300x225.jpg 300w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/IVI-team-768x576.jpg 768w, https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/IVI-team-600x450.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" /></a></p>
<p>Come out and join us next year at Onondaga Lake for a celebration of Haudenosaunee culture, traditional lacrosse, and traditional lacrosse sticks. We look forward to having even more teams in the tournament, and we are planning on having a lake team (house teams but at the lake) for those who want to play in the tournament but can’t put together a full team. We would love to have traditional indigenous peoples teams, and teams made up of lacrosse players of all backgrounds.</p>
<p>We also hope to have some pick-up scrimmages for players of all ages. Everyone will put their sticks in the middle and then sticks will be sorted into piles, and those will be the teams for some fun lighthearted pick-up game excitement.</p>
<p><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/laxweekend19/">Join us September 28-29, 2019 for the Haudenosaunee Woodenstick Festival and Randy Hall Memorial Tournament</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="https://indigenousvalues.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/slomo-video-alf-jacques-lacrosse-sticks-collections.mp4" length="3023133" type="video/mp4" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Draft: 2018 Wooden Stick Festival Schedule</title>
		<link>https://indigenousvalues.org/draft-2018-wooden-stick-festival-schedule/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DJ Brett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 16:47:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lacrosse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#laxweekend18]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haudenosaunee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Onondaga Lake]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Syracuse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wooden stick]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://indigenousvalues.org/?p=1832</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Deyhontsigwa&#8217;ehs-Creator’s Game, Lacrosse Weekend Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival &#38; Randy Hall Memorial Master’s Tournament 29 &#38; 30 September 2018 Onondaga Lake Park, Ball Fields Randy Hall Memorial Master’s Box Lacrosse Tournament About: 4 teams,Wooden stick preferred, leather ball. 20 minute &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/draft-2018-wooden-stick-festival-schedule/" aria-label="Draft: 2018 Wooden Stick Festival Schedule">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 style="text-align: center;">Deyhontsigwa&#8217;ehs-Creator’s Game,<br />
Lacrosse Weekend<br />
Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival<br />
&amp; Randy Hall Memorial Master’s Tournament<br />
29 &amp; 30 September 2018<br />
Onondaga Lake Park, Ball Fields</h2>
<h3></h3>
<h3>Randy Hall Memorial Master’s Box Lacrosse Tournament</h3>
<p>About: 4 teams,Wooden stick preferred, leather ball. 20 minute running clock halves, 5 minutes halftime</p>
<p>The teams are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Onondaga Masters</li>
<li>Rez Dogs</li>
<li>Mohawk</li>
<li>Buffalo</li>
</ol>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><strong>Saturday 29 September:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Game #1 11 AM</td>
<td>A v B</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Game #2 noon</td>
<td>B v C</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Game #3 1 PM</td>
<td>C v D</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Game #4 2 PM</td>
<td>A v D</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Game #5 3 PM</td>
<td>A v C</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Game #6 4 PM</td>
<td>B v D</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><strong>Sunday 30 September:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Game #7 10 AM</td>
<td> 1<sup>st</sup> seed v 4<sup>th</sup> seed</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Game #8 11 AM</td>
<td> 2<sup>nd</sup> seed v 3<sup>rd</sup> seed</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Game #9 Noon</td>
<td>losers of games #7 &amp; #8 play for bronze</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Game #10 1 PM</td>
<td>winners of Games #7 &amp; &amp; #8 play for gold and silver</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3>Haudenosaunee Wooden Stick Festival</h3>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><strong>Saturday 29 September:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11 AM &amp; 3 PM</td>
<td>Alf Jacques,<br />
[Jacques booth]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2 PM</td>
<td> Social Dancing and music,<br />
[exhibition tent]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Noon</td>
<td> Coach Desko &amp; SU Men’s Lacrosse team (?)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3PM</td>
<td> Talk by Iroquois Nationals</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><strong>Sunday 30 September:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11 AM &amp; 3 PM</td>
<td> Alf Jacques,<br />
[Jacques booth]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2PM</td>
<td> Social Dancing &amp; music,<br />
[exhibition tent]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Noon</td>
<td> Ansley Jemison,<br />
GM of Iroquois Nationals</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Draft Schedule for Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery</title>
		<link>https://indigenousvalues.org/draft-schedule-for-taking-on-the-doctrine-of-discovery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DJ Brett]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2018 17:41:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#docdis2018]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Catholicism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christianity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Colonialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[columbus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[doctrine of discovery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haudenosaunee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[indigenous values]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Onondaga Lake]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Onondaga Nation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Syracuse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[treaties]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://indigenousvalues.org/?p=1580</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Draft schedule of “Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery: What Are Our Next Steps?” Skä·noñh—Great Law of Peace Center, 6680 Onondaga Lake Parkway, Liverpool, New York 13088. Learn More about Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery: What are our Next &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="https://indigenousvalues.org/draft-schedule-for-taking-on-the-doctrine-of-discovery/" aria-label="Draft Schedule for Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Draft schedule of “<a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/taking-on-the-doctrine-of-discovery-what-are-our-next-steps/">Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery: What Are Our Next Steps?</a>”</h3>
<p>Skä·noñh—Great Law of Peace Center, 6680 Onondaga Lake Parkway, Liverpool, New York 13088.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/taking-on-the-doctrine-of-discovery-what-are-our-next-steps/">Learn More about Taking on the Doctrine of Discovery: What are our Next Steps?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://indigenousvalues.org/doctrine-of-discovery-conference-hotels/">Book Your Hotel</a></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<table id="sat18aug" class="wdn_responsive_table flush-left">
<caption>
<h4><strong>Saturday 18 August</strong></h4>
</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th id="sat18aug_row_0col_0" colspan="1">Time</th>
<th id="sat18aug_row_0col_1" colspan="1">Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">8:00 AM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Coffee, tea and light breakfast</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">8:30 AM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Opening– Thanksgiving Address</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">9:00 AM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Philip P. Arnold and Sandy Bigtree (<em>Mohawk Nation</em>) greeting and orientation to the Center and conference</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">10:00 AM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">“Indigenous Peoples of Turtle Island, Traditional Laws and Values”<br />
Betty Lyons (<em>Onondaga Nation</em>), Eve Reyes-Aguirre (<em>Izkaloteka Mexica Azteca</em>), Angela Mooney D’Arcy (<em>Acjachemen Nation</em>) (Lyons, moderator</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">11:30 AM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Papal Bull burning ceremony led by John Floberg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">12:30PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Traditional Haudenosaunee foods Lunch</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">1:30PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">&#8220;Strategic Responses to the Impacts of DOD on Urban Indigenous Peoples and Communities of Color&#8221; Nita Gonzales (<em>Tarahumara</em>), Roberto Borrero (<em>Taino</em>), Rick Chavolla (<em>Kumeyaay Nation</em>) (Bundy, moderator)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">2:30PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Break</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">2:45PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">How people are dealing with the Doctrine of Discovery in their own context or communities. Needed next steps, ideas, etc. Working Groups and breakout sessions led by – Boyet Ongkiko</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">4:15PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">“Next Steps.” Sandy Bigtree (<em>Mohawk Nation</em>), Tupac Enrique-Acosta (<em>Izkaloteka Mexica Azteca</em>), Aucán Huilcamán <em>(Mapuche)</em>, Jake Edwards <em>(Onondaga Nation)</em> (Arnold, moderator)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">5:30PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Traditional Haudenosaunee foods Banquet</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">6:30PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sat18aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Screening and discussion of “Even the Rain”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<table id="sun19aug" class="wdn_responsive_table flush-left">
<caption>
<h4><strong>Sunday 19 August</strong></h4>
</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th id="sun19aug_row_0col_0" colspan="1">Time</th>
<th id="sun19aug_row_0col_1" colspan="1">Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">8:00AM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Coffee, tea and light breakfast</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">9:00AM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Re-narrating our local stories and histories. Changing the message of the “French Fort” (Arnold, David McCallum)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">10:00AM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Panel: “United States Indian Law.” <span style="font-family: inherit; font-size: inherit;">Joe Heath, <a href="https://doctrineofdiscovery.org/resources-by-peter-derrico/">Peter D’Errico</a> and Steve Newcomb <em>(Shawnee, Lenape)</em> (Lyons, moderator)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">11:30AM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Tree planting ceremony at Center</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">12:30PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Traditional Haudenosaunee foods Lunch</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">1:30PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Assessment of the DoD in our midst. Round robin sharing session on next steps.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">4:00PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Water Ceremony at Onondaga Lake<br />
(we can ask people to bring the water from their various parts of the world for this event)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_0" data-header="Time">4:30PM</td>
<td colspan="1" headers="sun19aug_row_0col_1" data-header="Description">Closing. Tadodaho Sid Hill (<em>Onondaga Nation, Haudenosaunee Confederacy</em>)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
